29 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者辛美尔逝世的29年后）
RAAD REGION IN THE NORTHERN LANDS
（北方诸国 兰托地区）
It looks like there are all sorts of stores.
看来这里什么店都有呢
It'll be fun to shop here.
在这里逛街买东西一定很好玩
This is such a lively town.
真是热闹的城镇呢
There are so many bars.
有好多酒吧
That reminds me, Frieren. Let's go shopping together later.
对了 芙莉莲 待会一起去买东西吧
I think we'll find a lot of good shops here.
这里应该能找到很多不错的店铺
That's fine with me.
我是无所谓啦
What are you doing, Frieren? Let's go.
你在干什么 芙莉莲？要走了
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田钟人 作画：阿部司）
That's going a little too far!
你这样也太过分了吧
You're always so mean to me!
老是这样欺负我！
Do you hate me that much?
你就那么讨厌我吗？
Forget it! I'm going back to Master's place!
算了 我要回师父那里去！
Why is she always like that?
她干嘛老是这样啊？
Can't she listen to me for one second?
就不能听我解释一下吗？
What's all the fuss about? Is it a lover's quarrel?
吵吵闹闹的怎么了？ 是小情侣闹脾气吗？
Today is Fern's birthday.
今天是菲伦的生日
But Stark didn't get a present for her.
可是休塔尔克没有给她买礼物
And so Fern is furious.
所以菲伦就生气了
Honestly, I think you went overboard today.
老实说 我觉得 你今天做得有点过火了
You didn't even try to listen to Stark.
完全没给休塔尔克解释的机会
I didn't get you anything either.
我也什么都没准备
Men don't pay attention to small details such as
男人这种生物 不会去注意生日啦、纪念日
birthdays and anniversaries.
这种鸡毛蒜皮的小事情
Ouch! All right!
很疼耶 知道了啦！
I'll buy you something, so stop kicking.
我给你买就是了 别踢了
My knees are going to give out at this rate.
再这么踢下去 膝盖都要报废了
Jeez, I feel bad for Stark.
真是的 休塔尔克真可怜
At my age, even if I'm treated coldly, it's easier to brush it aside.
到了我这个年纪 就是被人冷眼相待也能不放在心上
But boys his age
但他那个年纪的男孩子
are easily affected by how girls treat them.
很容易就被女孩的举止所影响
I think it's best to go after him.
最好还是跟过去看看吧
I think you should go.
你应该要追过去比较好喔
Her hair accessory was a butterfly too, wasn't it?
说起来 她的发饰也是蝴蝶的设计
What a cute pouch.
真是可爱的钱包
-You hate it, don't you? -No.
-你不喜欢？ -没有
It's just off-putting that you seem so experienced.
只是你看起来很懂得讨女性欢心 所以让人有点不快罢了
Is that right…
这样啊…
Did you find Stark?
找到休塔尔克了吗？
He was at the plaza…
他刚刚在广场…
You couldn't approach him, huh?
你不敢接近他吧？
I know that you don't hate him.
我是知道的 你并不讨厌他
You just don't know how to deal with boys your age.
你只是不懂怎么 跟同龄的男孩子相处而已
Oh, the woes of youth.
真是青春呢
Anyway, you can pick out whichever one you want.
算了 你可以随便选你喜欢的
We can look at other shops too.
也可以去别家店看看
No, it's all right.
不用 没关系
Then I'll choose one myself.
那我就自己选了
In any case, you didn't have to get so mad just because he forgot a present.
话说回来 他只是忘了买礼物 你没有必要发这么大的火吧
He's obviously not the type to remember such details.
他显然不是那种会记得这种小事的人
I'll bet you he doesn't even remember his own birthday.
他说不定连自己的生日都不记得呢
Don't hold it against him.
因为这种事怪罪他也太可怜了
I gave Master Stark a present on his birthday.
休塔尔克大人生日时 我有送他礼物
Oh, really? Did you pick one out together that time?
是吗？当时礼物是一起挑的吗？
How did you know?
你是怎么知道的？
Usually, people don't refuse when you say, "Pick out whichever one you want."
如果有人说：“礼物随便你挑” 通常没有人会拒绝吧
In your mind, it's probably a special memory.
在你心里 那一定是很重要的回忆
Hence, you said "no" to me.
所以你才会拒绝我的提议
I'm not sure.
我也不知道
I just felt like doing it, that's all.
我只是想拒绝 就这样而已
Is that right?
这样吗？
Well then, hurry up and apologize and pick out a present with him.
既然如此 赶快去跟他道歉 然后跟他一起去挑礼物吧
He's still a kid.
毕竟他还只是个小鬼
He's not very intuitive.
脑袋并不是很灵光
You want to make up, right?
你想跟他和好吧？
You've got to use words to convey your feelings.
不把话说出口的话 对方是不会明白你心情的
You're right.
你说得对
-I'll go back to the inn. -Um…
-我先回旅店了 -那个…
I'm sorry for kicking you.
对不起 刚刚那样踢你
Master Stark.
休塔尔克大人
Fern…
菲伦…
-Um-- -I'm sorry!
-那个… -对不起！
The truth is, I wanted to pick something out together.
我其实是想跟你一起去挑礼物
Because I don't know what you like.
毕竟我不清楚你的喜好
But…
不过…
I was worried that you'd get upset if I said that.
我很担心这样说的话 会惹得你更不高兴
So I couldn't bring it up.
到头来就没说出口了
I wouldn't get upset.
我不会不高兴的
I'm sorry, Master Stark.
休塔尔克大人 对不起
I said things I shouldn't have.
我才是说了不该说的话
It's fine. I'm used to it.
没关系 我已经习惯了
I'm really sorry.
我真的很抱歉
Let's go.
走吧
Okay.
好
You're spying on them?
你在偷窥他们啊？
How classy of you, Frieren.
真是不错的嗜好呢 芙莉莲
Right back at you.
赞因你不也一样吗？
It seems they made up just fine.
看来他们有好好和好呢
As you become an adult,
人一旦长大成人
you learn how to deal with others
自然就知道 怎么把握人与人之间的距离感
and begin to avoid conflicts in general.
并且避免与他人发生冲突
Fighting like that is a privilege of the young.
像这样吵架是年轻人的特权呢
I bet they've been a handful, Frieren.
至今为了照顾他们 费了不少力气吧 芙莉莲
It's not easy taking care of kids.
毕竟他们都还只是小鬼
-How do you "deal with others"? -All three of you are kids, I guess.
-人跟人之间的距离感是什么？ -原来三个都是小鬼啊
Fern came up to me for advice.
菲伦来找我商量
Rather than you.
而不是去找你
I wonder who she's comparing me to and who she sees vicariously through me.
她究竟在我身上看到了谁的影子了？
Fern was raised by Heiter, after all.
毕竟菲伦是海塔抚养长大的
I can't stand to be compared with such an incredible priest.
拿我跟那样伟大的僧侣相比 真是不敢当
He's not incredible at all.
他一点都不伟大喔
He was a drunkard who was always suffering from a hangover.
他总是喝酒喝到宿醉
Is he an undead?
他是活死人吗？
He was so picky too.
而且很挑食
Stop that.
住手
-And he lied all the time. -I didn't drink.
-还老是说谎 -我没喝酒
He was nothing but a corrupt priest.
纯粹就是个酒肉僧侣而已
Although, you are even more corrupt than him, Sein.
不过赞因你这方面赢过他了 算是破戒僧了
Well, excuse me.
还真是抱歉喔
That's so surprising, though.
那还真是令人意外
From what I recall,
在我记忆里的海塔大人
Master Heiter was a kind and dependable grandpa.
一直是个温柔又可靠的爷爷
Unlike me, he was an ideal adult.
跟我不同 他是个理想的大人
You've changed, Heiter. You seem mature now.
海塔你变了呢 变成熟了
What are you saying? I'm an old grandpa already.
那是什么话？我都已经是个老爷爷了
You naturally turn this way as you get old.
随着年纪增长 自然就会变成这样了
Or so I'd like to say.
或者该说是我想这么说吧
But in truth, my heart has not changed much
但实际上 我的内心并没有什么改变
since I was a little kid.
跟小时候还是一样
This is just the accumulation
我只是以理想中的大人模样为目标
of my efforts to pretend to be mature in order to become my ideal adult.
努力装出成熟的样子 一路累积至今罢了
I'm sure I will
我相信我到死之前
have to pretend to be an adult until I die.
都会继续装作是个大人吧
Children need an adult in their lives
小孩子在他们的人生中
who can give them emotional support.
总需要一个大人能给予情感上的支持
Fern is especially a hard worker.
尤其像菲伦这么努力的孩子更是如此
I have to give her lots of commendation and guidance.
我必须给她大量的称赞与引导
Well then, who will commend you, for pretending to be an adult
那至死之前都装成大人模样的海塔
until you die?
有谁会来表扬呢？
That is what the Goddess is there for.
女神大人就是为此存在的
I'll have to wait until I go to heaven.
我只要等到上天国就好了
Then I'll commend you here.
那就由我在这里表扬你吧
Really?
真的吗？
But you probably don't understand how I feel as a human.
可是你并不了解人类的感情吧
How do you plan to commend me?
你打算怎么表扬我呢？
Surprisingly, this isn't too bad.
意外地做得不错嘛
Frieren, when I go to heaven,
芙莉莲 等到我上天国之后
I'll put in a good word for you.
我会向女神大人替你说几句好话的
I still think
我还是认为
you deserve to be commended by the Goddess.
你值得女神大人的夸奖
Is that so? I'll look forward to it then.
是这样吗？那我就拭目以待咯
What's this about, Frieren?
这是在干嘛 芙莉莲？
I think you're adulting just fine, Sein.
我觉得赞因有好好当个大人喔
It would've been so nice to be told that by an older lady.
这句话如果是 大姐姐来说的话就更好了
Then good for you.
那真是太好了
You can't get much older than me.
世上可没有 比我年纪更大的大姐姐了呢
29 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者辛美尔逝世的29年后）
BANDE WOODS IN THE NORTHERN LANDS
（北方诸国 邦德森林）
I appreciate it.
谢谢了
There were no horse-drawn buses around here, so you're a life saver.
附近都没有公共马车 你真是帮了我们大忙了
We need to help each other around here.
这种时候就该彼此互相帮助
I actually work as a merchant in the next village.
其实我在前面的村子做生意
My family runs an accessory shop.
我们家经营一家首饰店
Would you be interested?
你会有兴趣吗？
You're quite the businessman.
你还真是个生意人呢
That doesn't really interest me,
虽然我不大感兴趣
but Fern likes that kind of stuff. Oh?
不过菲伦蛮喜欢这类东西的 对吧？
You bought a new bracelet?
你买了新手镯？
Um…
这个…
This was…
这个是…
That's a cute design.
真可爱的设计
I have a ring with the same design.
我有只戒指的设计跟这个一样喔
I got it from Himmel.
是以前辛美尔送我的
I think it's matching.
应该跟你的是成套的
-Really? -Let's see…
-是这样吗？ -我找找喔
Where did I put it?
放哪里去了？
That's weird…
奇怪…
This is what you get for being messy.
不好好整理东西就会发生这种状况
Here it is.
找到了
I'm sorry. I let my guard down.
抱歉 是我大意了
Bird monsters are cunning and skilled at hiding their mana.
鸟类魔物向来狡猾 而且善于隐藏魔力
What should we do?
该怎么办？
Once we take down the monster,
总之先打倒魔物
can't we somehow get to safety with flight magic?
再用飞行魔法安全降落 不行吗？
You can make a wagon float, right?
你可以让马车飘浮起来吧？
Stark,
休塔尔克
have you ever seen a flying wagon?
你看过会飞的马车吗？
We're in one right now.
现在我们就坐在上面啊
It may come as a surprise,
说出来你或许会感到意外
but it's not even been 40 years
但是人类成功飞上天
since mankind learned how to fly.
这件事都还没有四十年
Up until then,
在那之前
the sky was monopolized by demons and monsters.
天空是魔族跟魔物的天下
The flight magic that mankind uses
人类所使用的飞行魔法
is just a reproduction of the spell that demons use.
是直接把 魔族使用的术式照搬过来用…
Enough of the complicated details.
那些难懂的细节就跳过吧
Say it in a way that I can understand.
用我能懂的方式解释一下
We don't know the logic behind the spell, so we can't adapt it as we wish.
我们并不清楚这种魔法术式的原理 所以无法随心所欲地应用
If it's larger than a human, we can only make it fly for a little bit.
如果是大于人类体型的物品 我们只能让它浮起一段时间
-I see. -We have no choice but to escape.
-原来如此 -看来只能放弃马车了
I'll fly with the merchant.
商人就由我带着飞
-Fern, you take Sein. -Understood.
-菲伦 赞因交给你 -知道了
I'll get our luggage together.
我去收拾大家的行李
Hey, what about me?
等一下 那我呢？
-Stark, you jump off. -What the heck is she saying?
-休塔尔克 你就跳下去吧 -说什么鬼话？
I think I will die.
我会死的耶
A warrior wouldn't die from this height.
战士从这种高度跳下去是不会死的吧
Of course I'd die!
当然会好不好！
Why are you looking at me like I'm crazy?
你干嘛一脸 不知道我在说什么的样子？
That's strange.
真奇怪
Eisen could free fall from any height and be completely unharmed.
不管从什么高度自由落体 艾泽都能毫发无伤
What is wrong with him?
这家伙有病吧？
Heiter was left speechless.
海塔都震惊到说不出话来了
The fact that he was left speechless
“震惊到说不出话”就表示
means Master Eisen was not normal.
艾泽大人已经不是个正常人了
Then why don't we make the wagon float
那么 在快要撞到地面时
right before we hit the ground?
把马车浮起来的话怎么样？
We have to calculate whether we can counterbalance our free fall.
那就得好好计算 怎么中和自由落体的速度
If we can't neutralize the momentum, we'll become minced meat.
如果没能中和掉的话 我们就会摔成肉饼了
She said something scary right now!
说的这是什么吓人的话啊！
Either way, we should probably act fast.
不管怎么样 我们可能要尽快行动
This type of monster hunts by smashing its prey on the ground.
这种魔物是透过摔死猎物来狩猎的
I see.
这样啊
You never know unless you try, I guess.
不试试看也不知道结果呢
Don't drop us so suddenly!
不要突然让我们掉下去啊！
I'm alive?
我…我还活着？
It seems it was a success.
看来是成功落地了
-You call this a success? -What sort of plan was that?
-这样能叫成功落地？ -这是哪门子的计划？
The horse had minor injuries, but they've been treated.
马只受了轻伤 不过已经治好了
The wagon is in bad shape, though. We need to repair it.
但马车的话就坏得不象样了 必须要修理才行
-Sorry… -Not at all. I'm so grateful.
-抱歉了 -哪里的话 我很感激你呢
If I was alone, I'd be dead by now.
如果只有我自己一个人 现在八成已经死了
We'll be busy repairing the wagon for a while.
看来要花点时间修马车了
Oh? That's weird…
咦？奇怪…
Where did it go?
跑去哪里了？
It's getting warm these days.
这几天开始变暖和了
It might be time to change our wardrobes.
差不多是时候把衣服换季了
By the way, where did that bracelet come from?
对了 菲伦 那个手镯是哪里来的？
It was a birthday present from Master Stark.
这是休塔尔克大人送我的生日礼物
It took me three hours to pick out.
我可是花了三个小时挑的
You ended up picking it yourself?
结果还是你自己挑啊？
I asked him to pick something out.
是我要他选给我的
I see.
原来如此
That must've been tough, Stark. That's the hardest position to be in.
一定很累人吧 休塔尔克 那是最麻烦的类型了
Tell me about it.
就是说啊
Is this okay?
这个可以吗？
I spent three hours trying to read her mood.
我整整三个小时都在看她脸色
-It was unbearable. -Poor you.
-感觉我都要窒息死了 -你还真是可怜
-I can hear everything. -But…
-我全都听到了 -不过…
I'm glad she likes it.
她能喜欢就好了
I'm impressed, Stark.
话说回来 你还真厉害
I thought you'd be more cowardly.
我本以为你属于更胆小的类型呢
That design is a mirrored lotus.
那种款式是镜莲花的设计
It means "eternal love."
花语是“永恒的爱”
In this region, it's something you give your lover.
这里的人都会给恋人送这种东西喔
-Master Stark. -I… I didn't know!
-休塔尔克大人 -我…我哪会知道这种事啊！
This is a misunderstanding!
这是个误会！
Do you think I know the meaning of flowers?
你认为我会知道花语什么的吗？
You have a point. You're stupid after all.
说得对 毕竟你是个笨蛋嘛
She's harsher than usual!
比平常说话更恶毒了！
You didn't know either.
明明你自己也不知道啊
-Did you say something? -It's nothing.
-你刚刚说什么？ -没什么
Um, should I replace it with something else?
那个…还是我拿去换成别的？
You gave this to me after thinking long and hard about it.
这可是你认真考虑挑来送我的礼物
Don't you ever ask that again.
请不要再说这种话了
I'm sorry!
对不起嘛！
What is it?
怎么了吗？
It's nothing.
没什么
Mistress Frieren.
芙莉莲大人
The wagon is all repaired,
马车已经都修好了
so we're leaving early tomorrow morning.
所以我们明天一大早就会离开
Okay.
这样啊
You've been sneaking out every night.
您每天晚上都偷溜出来
What are you looking for?
是在找什么东西呢？
The ring Himmel gave me.
辛美尔送我的戒指
I'll look too.
我也来找
We'll stay here until we find it.
我们找到之后再离开吧
It's fine.
不要紧
If I don't find it tonight, I'll give up.
今晚要是没找到 我就会放弃了
I'm used to losing things.
反正我已经习惯丢三落四了
Plus, that wasn't the only thing I received from Himmel.
而且我从辛美尔那里收到的 也不是只有那枚戒指
It was a ring with the same mirrored lotus design as this, right?
那枚戒指跟这个手镯 一样有镜莲花吧？
Apparently, that flower means "eternal love."
据说花语是“永恒的爱”
Yeah? I didn't know.
是吗？我不知道
It doesn't matter.
那种事怎么样都好
I'm sure Himmel didn't know about the meaning either.
我相信辛美尔当年也不知道它的花语
Even then…
就算如此…
I'm sure it's very precious.
我认为那枚戒指一定是很重要的东西
We should all search together.
让大家一起来找吧
You should have told me!
你应该早点告诉我的！
There were always people in the village who lost
村里总是会有人弄丢
their accessories.
他们的装饰品
It's a spell for finding lost accessories.
这是寻找丢失装饰品的魔法
It's one of the spells that I planned
我原本就打算把这个魔法
to give you as this time's reward.
当作这次委托的报酬之一送给你
Frieren,
芙莉莲
you worked really hard during this time's subjugation quest.
这次的讨伐委托你真的很拼命呢
Go ahead and pick whatever you want.
从这里随便挑一个你喜欢的吧
Accessories, huh?
首饰吗？
I'd rather go to a magic shop.
去魔法商店的话我会更开心的
-This is fine. -That was fast.
-那就这个吧 -挑这么快啊
Put some more thought into it.
稍微多花点心思吧
What's wrong?
怎么了吗？
It's nothing.
没什么
Frieren…
芙莉莲…
Thanks.
谢了
It's a good thing you didn't give up, Mistress Frieren.
幸好您没放弃呢 芙莉莲大人
You might be right.
或许是吧
By the way, why is Fern wearing a mirrored lotus bracelet?
话说回来 菲伦为什么 戴着有镜莲花的手镯呢？
Because Master Stark is stupid.
那是因为休塔尔克大人是笨蛋啊
How mean.
好过分
-I know spells for combat too. -I feel anxious.
-我也知道战斗用的魔法 -我感觉痒痒的
-He's not as talented as his brother. -Yes, father.
-他不像他哥哥那样有天赋 -是的 父亲
This isn't good.
不妙
-This is hell. -We should hurry.
-根本是地狱啊 -必须加紧脚步
"Smells Like Trouble."
《麻烦事的气息》
Let's go to the next village.
我们去下一个村子吧
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译：洪贞韵